The slow passage of time on objects
>> [music]
>> exposes these to all kinds of
aggression.
External [music] agents and human
activity act on them, damaging them,
wearing them out, rusting them, rotting
them.
Water, fire, insects, [music] and
microorganisms are together with man
their fiercest enemies.
What makes man different [music] from
the other forces
is that they are the only ones who can
stop or hold back the process,
>> [music]
>> which with other intervention would be
irreversible.
Scientific interest in art conservation
has developed over the last century
based [music] on science and technology.
The main criterion is that nothing that
is external or foreign to the piece
should be added.
In those cases where it is essential to
transgress this general principle,
[music]
two requirements should be rigorously
met.
Whatever has been added should be
clearly appreciated,
and it should also be possible to remove
it without this jeopardizing the
integrity of the whole.
Moreover, in many cases,
it is necessary for the piece of work to
recover its function [music] and
arrangement.
These requirements are the result of the
experience accumulated by curators
who have learned [music] that a piece of
work is never definitively restored.
Technical advances occur very quickly,
and respect for what [music] could be
done in the future
makes restorers work cautiously so that
the current intervention does not
obstruct [music] future restorations.
>> [music]
>> Grand official buildings are historical
scenarios and are both the symbols and
the showcases of nations.
>> We must fix our vision on what real
peace would bring.
Peace, after all,
means not just avoiding war
and the costs of preparing for it.
>> The halls of these buildings are the
scene of events which affect us all.
Sometimes they are even privileged
enough to witness the signing of
treaties which constitute the first
building blocks of a fragile peace.
The area where the Royal Palace in
Madrid now stands has been a center of
power since the earliest times.
But the first stone for the building
which stands here today was laid only
two and a half centuries ago and this
palace replaced an older one built by
the Austrian dynasty which fell a victim
to fire.
This enormous building and everything
[music] which it contains is a very
important part of the Spanish National
Trust.
The Spanish National Trust deals [music]
with the state heritage which is at the
disposal of the crown.
This great group [music] of palaces and
monasteries also contains some splendid
and valuable collections of [music]
artworks.
All these works are at the disposal and
service of His Majesty the King so that
he can carry out state functions, and
they are also [music] at the service of
all people as a permanent conveyor of
our culture.
All these riches and this heritage from
our history demand constant care,
protection, and [music] restoration so
that they remain in perfect condition.
For this reason, the [music] National
Trust has a number of workshops where
the necessary restoration can be carried
out.
>> [music]
>> Here we are entering the very heart of
the palace, the throne room.
The throne room is spacious, but it is
neither arrogant nor imposing in its
dimensions, and was designed by the
[music] educated and prudent monarch
Charles III.
The symbols with which it is decorated
reflect more than anything else the
character of the monarch who occupied
the throne at the time.
Around the throne itself, the four
theological virtues are represented:
prudence, justice, strength, and
moderation.
Fit companions for one who wielded
absolute power.
>> [music]
>> The wish to maintain the palace as a
living building demands constant effort
from all those who are responsible for
its care and maintenance.
The enormous number of works of art held
within its walls, and their high quality
and historical value, mean that the
conditions under which their
conservation is carried out have to be
constantly monitored.
There are kilometers of halls and rooms
full of stuccoes, drapes, gilded
objects, [music] tapestries, clocks,
porcelain, chandeliers, mirrors,
furniture, pictures, and carpets, which
have to be kept in perfect condition in
spite of the hundreds of tourists and
the additional enormous effort needed
for their conservation which this
implies.
There's one particular part of the
National Trust which consists of all the
halls of the palace where state
functions are held,
the presentation of credentials, state
banquets, audiences, and this means that
it is not only necessary to restore the
room itself, but to restore it so that
it can be used, since it is not the same
thing to keep a work of art in a glass
case as to keep it in a hall in the very
place where it was intended [music] to
be displayed.
The vast range of different materials
and objects with which the restoration
studios of the palace faced requires a
small army of specialists who are fully
acquainted with the technical details
and production processes long forgotten
or abandoned over the years.
And they also need to know about
materials which are no longer in current
use at the beginning of the 21st
century.
In some cases, the old traditions cannot
be learned from books, but are handed
down from generation to generation.
>> This is the case with the Tomasso family
who have worked in the palace for
generations.
In the workshops of these studios,
modern techniques are used for the
treatment of various pieces. Ultrasonic
techniques, for example, are used for
the cleaning of delicate surfaces.
>> [music]
>> The collection contained in the Royal
Armory is priceless from a purely
historical point of view, as well as on
account of the precision of the
different mechanisms.
Specialists first turn to documentation
contained in the archives, where even
the smallest details of each weapon are
recorded before beginning any
restoration.
A vast range of restoration techniques
are employed since many different
objects from different places have been
collected over the years.
These pieces, on account of the
decorations which have been applied, are
truly unique.
Embossed with coral, mother of pearl,
and precious stones, they seem more like
jewels or personal adornments than
firearms.
The furniture in the palace, which
encompasses several different areas and
styles, is the responsibility of the
joinery and upholstery department, and
it is here that the necessary
adjustments and repairs are carried out
to keep the furniture in good condition.
But the various different departments
scarcely ever operate in isolation since
many works of restoration draw on
several different areas of expertise.
In an environment like a palace, each
individual piece also forms a part of
and is understood within the context of
the general decoration and architecture
dictated by a particular historical
style.
>> One important area in the upkeep of the
palace as a whole is the restoration of
the gilded surfaces, which cover some
hundreds of square meters.
Gilders work using traditional
techniques, which incorporate knowledge
acquired over centuries.
Machines are unable to duplicate their
ability to manually handle and apply the
fine gold leaf.
From the point of view of restoration,
the most important thing in this room is
the old upholstery, which has to be
cleaned and kept in a textile depository
so that it is available for researchers.
But in order to be able to use the room
again in its original form, it is
necessary to re-upholster it with cloth
of the same kind as that which exists
now.
The restoration of large upholstered
surfaces has to be accomplished in such
a way that the building is in a perfect
state and can continue to be used.
But in the textile workshop in the
palace, work is also undertaken on other
types of pieces and research is
constantly being carried out.
There are also numerous ceramic pieces
in the palace.
>> [music]
>> Quite apart from [music] the valuable
individual ceramic objects placed in
rooms and on tables, there [music] are
whole rooms where the decoration is
based on ceramic reliefs.
>> [music]
>> The Royal Palace in Madrid also contains
many other exceptional artifacts amongst
its treasures.
The section for gold artifacts include
[music] some very remarkable pieces, as
well as some unusual miniature and
whimsical decorative articles like this
circular alabaster [music] shrine made
during the first third of the 19th
century.
>> [music]
>> Reliquaries designed to hold the remains
of martyrs and [music] saints were also
in most cases made of precious metals.
>> [music]
>> This nativity scene made [music] from
wood, coral, silver, copper, and brass
during the first half of the 16th
century is an exquisite and delicate
piece of work.
>> [music]
>> Each piece has its own history and forms
an integral part of the group.
This jewel case [music] belonging to
Isabel II
is a miniature safe. It is very easy to
open when you know how, but if not, it
would be a challenge to a thief even
today.
Then there are the [music] clocks.
The hands have turned for centuries, and
they have been witness to the rhythms of
war and peace,
>> [music]
>> to weddings and funerals, and to joys
and sorrows.
>> These [music] are pieces which move and
even have a voice.
They're monuments to the skills of the
clockmakers
and their precision movements are only
fully appreciated [music] when the
moment comes to restore them.
>> [music]
[music]
>> There are clocks of all different kinds,
decorated in all different ways.
They are in turn ornamental, scientific,
coquettish, solemn, precisely accurate,
[music]
and pretentious.
There are planetary clocks, astral
clocks, and clocks reflecting the stars,
all ceaselessly marking the passage of
time.
>> The trust, of course, has [music] a
painting studio as well, although most
of the Spanish royal collection was
transferred to the Prado Museum when it
was first established.
The part of the collection [music] which
now hangs on the palace walls portrays
previous occupants of the building,
former kings and queens who seem to be
saying farewell to the groups of [music]
tourists who have completed their visit
to this amazing collection of curious
and wonderful objects.
Very few of them are aware of the
efforts being carried out daily [music]
to preserve and look after what they
have just seen.
There are places in the world where it
is clear that more lies behind what is
immediately visible.
Places where a special silence reigns.
Where the word has a special meaning.
The library in El Escorial on the
outskirts of Madrid is one of these
special magnetic places.
Conversations overheard in this room
have without a doubt brought something
invisible to it.
A certain sensitivity. Since from its
very creation this room was intended to
be a spiritual point.
With a certain spirituality which is not
necessarily linked to that of religion.
It was in this room that the world was
analyzed for this was the center of
activity of the Spanish Empire at a time
when the sun did not set within its
bounds.
The very best brains of the Catholic
world, who were philosophers,
geographers, astronomers, alchemists, or
who sometimes combined all disciplines,
used the library in El Escorial as their
base and as the source of information.
A veneer of doubts and certainties, of
wisdom and ignorance, of beliefs and
mistakes, gives these objects their own
personality in that they have witnessed
the efforts of human intelligence to
come to terms with the world in which it
finds itself.
The monastery of El Escorial, considered
to be the eighth wonder of the world, is
on the outskirts of Madrid. Its
conservation was awarded to the national
trust, and in total it is many times
larger than the Royal Palace in Madrid.
A high price in terms of restoration
must be paid to keep the building alive
and open to visitors.
The lower part of these frescoes, for
example, which is within reach of
visitors, has been restored.
But we are not talking about a modern
problem, since they are also graffiti
which date back to the 8th century.
Attempts were made to protect it with
glass panels, but tourists [music] push
coins between the glass and the wall and
cause considerable damage to the
painting.
When one considers El Escorial, it seems
that it is endless.
>> [music]
>> Room after room follow on in endless
succession.
Restoration work here is monumental for
the simple reason that the monastery
itself is so huge and imperial.
For Spain, the 16th century was the high
point in its entire history, and El
Escorial is the perfect embodiment of
the importance of the age.
Its straight, clean lines reflect the
severity of Castile,
and were it not for the addition of some
color and embellishment, it would look
very ominous.
>> [music]
>> This is why the religious frescoes were
originally introduced, and they
represent the best paintings of this
type of their time.
This was not the first time that they
have undergone restoration.
They have always been within the reach
of visitors, [music]
and some people have felt the necessity
to leave some mark of their visit, to
scratch a desperate record of their
existence as the years flowed by.
It is a very human temptation, and after
all, even the artists themselves [music]
left their own mark behind.
>> [music]
[music]
>> But finally, their time came for the
marks to disappear in the hands
[clears throat] of the restorers who
have made every effort to return these
maltreated painted surfaces to their
original [music] brilliance and
freshness.
The scratches which have marks on them
are first stuccoed and then hidden with
color.
A hushed music seems to descend from the
empirical scene, a solemn symphony, the
noise of stirring bodies congregating
around the glory of the Spanish monarch
in the 16th century.
>> [music]
>> Fortunately, no one has managed to reach
the magnificent paintings which decorate
the ceiling of the principal staircase.
They are too high up and they give the
impression of being even higher.
This place, which is huge and bare, is
so impressive that it seems to have a
paralyzing effect.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The various works of restoration which
were carried [music] out in El Escorial
were not independent of one another.
>> [music]
>> There was an overall concept of
restoring the grandiose building in its
entirety.
Situated as it is in the mountains north
of Madrid, it has been subjected to a
mountain climate for centuries.
>> [music]
>> And although the fabric of the building,
which is made of granite, is not in
danger, the passing of time has had some
effect on some of [music] the patios and
roofs.
The greatest restoration efforts in the
monastery concentrated in the so-called
Sala de Batallas or Hall of Battles.
According to some tapestries which were
discovered centuries later in the palace
at Segovia, Taborone, Cambiaso,
Granello, and Castello began the
paintings here in 1585.
There is evidence of 16 quite extensive
restorations since the 17th century.
For this restoration, the 17th, they
estimated that it would be necessary to
employ a team of 10 specialists for a
period of 3 and 1/2 years.
But it was hard to estimate with any
precision since in this kind of work
time can be multiplied two to five times
as unforeseen circumstances crop up
during the course of the process.
The real problems which are likely to
arise cannot be identified until the
conservation work begins.
And only then can the restorer have any
idea of the extent of the work which
faces him.
The battle against persistent humidity,
the discovery of original paintings
underneath repainted areas, as well as
other possible surprises of this
magnitude or even greater magnitude will
serve to make the restorer cautious and
any prior estimates are couched with
reservations.
The painting of a fresco also made its
own demands in terms of timing.
The artists who carried it out began
preparing the plaster many months in
advance.
And any decision which was made in a
hurry could well have had bad
repercussions for work carried out in
the Hall of Battles.
As for the frescos themselves, the
detailed work which the painting
requires and the criteria of modern
restoration
meant that a meticulous rigatino arch
should be used instead of traditional
repainting. And this made the work of
the restorer very much more complicated.
But on the other hand, it meant that the
restoration of the work and its
authenticity was far better than any
previous work carried out in the Hall of
Battles.
But why is it called the Hall of
Battles?
Perhaps because power always needs a
reminder that it must overcome other
powers in order to survive.
Sometimes it even needs to overcome its
own power.
Here power confronts power. Lance
confronts lance. Helmet confronts
helmet.
Just like warring rams following some
atavistic impulse and multiplying the
tombs of the dead.
Cannons, banners waving in the wind,
polished armor violently shining in the
sun.
Spurs digging into the horses flanks.
The steaming crossbows, unbelievable
wounds, shouts of rage and of anguish.
The desperate neighing of horses,
implacable cavalry squadrons opening up
a route through ranks of infantry like a
combine harvester moving through the
grain fields.
These men however have faith in what
they are doing. They are the defenders
of the king, of the faith, of the pope,
and of the fatherland.
They sense the weight of history and
they go into combat willingly and with
determination.
What else could make them lift up their
arms if not conviction?
It was complete conviction which made
them wield their swords and complete
conviction which led to so many
committed dead men.
El Escorial is a surprising mix of love
and violence because it was built as a
result of spiritualism combined with
power.
It is not a beautiful building but it
was never intended to be so. It is
awesome and attracts and terrifies at
one and the same time. It is not
amenable, but severe. It is distance
[music]
and unwelcoming, but remains aloof.
Nothing could be more alien to our own
time and our own customs than these
imposing walls which offer no sanctuary.
This construction of straight lines
which does not make the slightest
concession. These angles and borders
which seem to want to purify thought and
faith until they become pure abstract
[music] geometry.
But even so, it has an awesome beauty of
its own.
At the beginning of the 13th century,
the city of Burgos was the seat of the
court of Castile.
And in 1221, the first stone was laid of
what would become one of the most
beautiful cathedrals in the Catholic
world.
Now almost eight centuries later,
[music] its delicate structures are
still standing and bear witness to the
zeal and dedication of its builders.
But time has taken [music] its toll and
only timely intervention to restore the
building has put a stop to further
deterioration.
The scaffolding which was erected
[music] around it to carry out the
restoration gave the church a curiously
modern appearance and the Gothic
cathedral lied hidden behind what looked
like an office building.
The square constructions which masked
the delicate patterns of its towers also
served to highlight the harmonious
proportions of the original building.
>> [music]
>> Any attempt to restore these stone
needles which are covered with sculpted
reliefs is an enormous undertaking.
Especially when one realizes that this
is not a task which is limited [music]
to the surfaces of the structure, but
which goes deep into the structure
itself.
The surface of the cathedral [music] had
been affected by the passage of time.
Accumulated dirt over the centuries had
concentrated [music]
in those areas which escaped naturally
being washed off by the rain.
>> [music]
>> And at these points, the surface of the
stone had reacted with the chemical
agents which had fallen on it.
>> [music]
>> The result was a progressive
deterioration of the surface which had
caused successive layers of stone to
break away, and which could in the end
destroy the stone completely.
This was the reason for the leprous
effect on certain parts, parts which
were once intricately carved and
polished.
Preliminary research precedes any
restoration work. It is imperative to
know in detail how the micro processes
which are taking place in the stone have
come about.
Just like hospital patients, these
reliefs yield data through sensitive
instruments which will later be
carefully analyzed by specialists.
The whole monument was threatened by
deterioration, and the anxious
specialists undertook extensive studies
of the general condition of the whole
church, and discovered that the two
needles were in greatest danger since
they were originally constructed of
stone openwork to save weight.
Deterioration of the towers of the
cathedral in Burgos is divided into
three distinct types.
The inevitable aging of the material of
which they are made, the effect of the
level of industrialization of
contemporary society,
>> [music]
>> and the damage caused by man.
In the towers, unlike the rest of the
cathedral, the effects of pollution have
been minimal since they stand over 80 m
above ground.
>> [music]
[music]
>> But man has had a negative effect on the
towers. In the 30s a metal structure was
introduced to support the bells in the
staircase leading up to the balcony on
top of the tower.
But the structure was completely
independent from the tower itself.
>> [music]
>> A lack of knowledge in the 60s led to
this metal structure being concreted to
the stones of the towers themselves.
The corrosion of the metal structure
over the years produced a wave effect
which caused the stone towers to crack
and some cracks now measure more than 4
cm.
>> [music]
>> The solution has been to micro sew the
cracks together, but in particular to
isolate the negative influence which the
metal structure was having through the
concrete. By making the two structures
independent of one another.
>> [bell]
>> One of the towers has already been
restored and the scaffolding has been
removed. And it is possible to see the
detail which the cleaning process has
revealed such as these fine carvings all
along the edge of the structure.
The stone masons knew that their work
would not be visible from the ground,
but this in no way affected the quality
of their work.
>> Work on surfaces as complex as these has
to be very precisely planned, and the
exact measurement of each one of the
thousands of elements which make up the
pattern was calculated and recorded.
A supplementary technique, known as
photometrics, is of great assistance in
the restoration of buildings.
The photometrics department of the
Spanish Institute of Historical Heritage
can provide plans by using pairs of
photographs taken with special cameras,
which are linked to precise
topographical points.
Plates are put into an optical apparatus
called a restorer, where a stereoscopic
image of the monument is generated,
which the operator can interpret using
both his hands and his feet.
The results are rendered by an automatic
design machine which transfers the
various operations onto paper.
The relationship which exists between
the distance between various parts of
the building and their size is therefore
mathematically guaranteed.
The restored image can be generated to
an appropriate scale for the subsequent
work of restoring the monument.
The resulting plans are an insurance for
the future in the conservation of these
architectural treasures, since they
ensure that any future work will be
carried out with complete precision.
The vault of the dome of the cathedral
in Burgos is a reminder that it is on
the inside that the building really
comes into its own.
The interior of the cathedral is even
more impressive than the exterior.
On the walls and the internal
structures, stone [music] has been
transformed into figures, flowers, and
swords.
A petrified world full of messages and
symbols, stone filigree erected by and
in the service of Christianity.
The church as the owner of these
architectural jewels has been dedicated
to their conservation since the very
beginning.
And there is even an ecclesiastical post
which reflects this task, that of the
church warden, [music] that is as old as
the cathedrals themselves.
He is appointed by the chapter and is in
charge of all works carried out within
the cathedral, is responsible for
identifying all the needs of the
building, and is especially responsible
for the conservation of the building
itself, as well as of all the artifacts
which the building contains.
The interior restoration of the
cathedral's chapels turned the church
into a forest of scaffolding, a
three-dimensional spider's web which the
restorer had to learn to navigate with
ease.
Platforms on different levels allowed
access to the highest areas, right up
into the heavens.
Restorers were thus able to reach parts
of the cathedral which had not been seen
since the building was constructed.
But everywhere, even in the hidden
recesses, there was the same striving
for perfection and the same careful
attention to detail.
There are 2 km of reliefs like these,
for example, in this chapel alone.
Detailed restoration provides an
opportunity to study in depth some of
the little-known aspects of the
construction techniques and the
sculpture of the Middle Ages.
And the more that is learned, the more
surprises there are in store.
It is clear the cathedrals offer much
more than they appear to do so at first
sight.
And there is still much more to be
learned.
Not very long after America was
discovered, the Admirals from Castile
decided to endow the cathedral of Burgos
with something that later would be
considered one of the best ornamental
groups of religious art that were
carried out at that time.
Five centuries later, the altarpieces
that composed what was called Constable
Chapel were dismantled for its
restoration in the same cathedral
enclosure.
The complexity of this intervention can
be judged by the state and the quality
of the sizes that once restored, they
should adjust to each other with the
precision of a clockwork mechanism.
During the process, the director of the
restoration was forced to take [music]
very radical decisions.
One of them was to make copies of the
most important pieces in the group that
would replace the original ones when the
altarpiece was installed again. [music]
That way, the originals would be
exhibited so that the public would have
occasion of appreciating close up the
extraordinary quality that up until now
went unnoticed due to the high places
where the pieces were.
This decision had another reason not
less [music] justified.
It allowed for example to maintain
original pieces in more appropriate
environmental conditions and safe from
new attacks of xylophag insects.
On the other hand, the decision
respected a basic rule.
All these copies could be replaced again
by their originals whenever this was
required.
It is essential to insist on making the
extraordinary effort that involves this
work on these masterpieces of medieval
and Renaissance carving.
To finance all this effort was necessary
to obtain the support of private
individuals and entities.
Society can also contribute with an
effective way to the best conservation
and restoration of monuments and very
especially of the wealth contained
inside these big cathedrals.
>> [music]
>> The exhibition of the imagery of the
Condestable Chapel's altarpieces is an
example of this action shared between
associations and institutions and the
result that one can achieve with these
kind of procedures.
In the Condestable Chapel, there is not
only one altarpiece but several that
include exceptional pieces
>> [music]
>> as the Santa Ana triplex of Gil de
Siloé.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Or this nativity original his son, Diego
de Siloe, with serious deteriorations in
the boy's figure.
Or the elegant angel of the announcement
painted by Felipe de Bigarny.
>> [music]
>> The average quality of the pieces is
really extraordinary.
And so are these strange symbols they
sometimes have.
>> [music]
>> Like in the case of this singular piece
known as the synagogue, whose gloomy
force is still more accentuated by the
curious circumstance that the xylophage
insects chose to attack the most
dramatic area in the carving.
It is very remarkable that most of these
sacred sculptures appear sustaining
books in their hands.
The books certainly are also sacred,
[music]
and the artist scruple wrote on their
pages even knowing that due to its
position on the alter place, the detail
could not be appreciated.
>> [music]
>> People who are in daily contact with
this national heritage carry out the
vital service of both watching over it
and educating others about it.
But they obviously cannot carry [music]
out all the work themselves.
They need the help of a specialist to
tackle large works of art like this one.
This is one of the largest works by
Claudio Coello [music] and was made in
1668.
It was actually made in situ and then
placed [music] on this wall.
The whole altarpiece was built around it
afterwards and that is why it is so
difficult to restore.
These are polychromes which were lifted
up in pans and fixed with steam.
There've been several attempts at
restoration over recent years and above
all one attempt which was the worst of
all during the 19th century which has
been totally removed.
The original colors used by Claudio
Coello can now be seen in all their
glory just as he intended.
The resources seem quite limited when
one considers the enormous amount of
work [music] required to maintain the
vast quantity of statues, carvings,
porticoes, freezes, columns and
paintings which are all part of the
national heritage.
>> [music]
>> Many of these pieces portray scenes from
the past which together provide valuable
information for understanding the past
centuries.
And which may seem very prolific judging
from the extraordinary heritage they
have left us.
>> [music]
[music]